<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>news | The Commission for the Management and Application of Geoscience Information</title><link>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/tag/news/</link><atom:link href="https://cgi-iugs.github.io/tag/news/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>news</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 23:01:15 +0100</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/images/logo_hu5f245ccb47af51e4024f06ef3a708f7f_150866_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url><title>news</title><link>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/tag/news/</link></image><item><title>CGI council elections</title><link>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/elections/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 23:01:15 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/elections/</guid><description>&lt;p>Nominations for CGI Council for 2020–24 are open. Any CGI member can nominate to serve on the council to help organise CGI&amp;rsquo;s standards programme and the outreach activities of the CGI. Councillors must have support to be able to attend annual council meetings (the next one will be at the 36th IGC in Delhi in March 2020) and to devote time to implement CGI&amp;rsquo;s mission.
&lt;a href="https://cgi-iugs.github.io/misc/councilapp/">Full procedures&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CGI Award for Young Earth Scientists at the 36th IGC</title><link>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/cgiaward/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 23:01:43 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/cgiaward/</guid><description>&lt;p>CGI sponsors an award to assist early career scientists to present at conferences such as the IGC on the use of CGI standards in data delivery and analysis. The award covers up to US$2000 towards the cost of travel and accommodation at the IGC in Delhi. Registration cost is covered by the Young Earth Scientists (YES) Network.
&lt;a href="https://cgi-iugs.github.io/docs/CGI_YES_award_2019-20.pdf">Full details&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Applications for the 36th IGC award close on 15 October 2019.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>36th International Geological Congress</title><link>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/36thigc/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 23:01:29 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/36thigc/</guid><description>&lt;p>Abstracts are invited to the special symposium
&lt;a href="https://www.36igc.org/science-program" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Advances in geoscience data sharing and processing&lt;/a> (Theme 45.10) at the 36th International Geological Congress (IGC). The symposium will highlight new techniques, standards, and algorithms for managing, delivering, visualising and analysing geoscience data both globally and regionally, including &amp;lsquo;big&amp;rsquo; data. The symposium is jointly organised by CGI, IAMG, and OneGeology.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>New EarthResourceML-Lite v2.0.1</title><link>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/ermllitereleased/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 23:02:08 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/ermllitereleased/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;a href="http://earthresourceml.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EarthResourceML-Lite&lt;/a> is a data model and schema for simple map services (e.g. WMS and WFS Simple Features). It is an abridged version of the full EarthResourceML model and can be used to deliver simplified views on mineral occurrences and their commodities, mines, mining activities and mine waste products.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>IUGS Deep-time Digital Earth program</title><link>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/iugsdde/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2018 23:02:58 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/iugsdde/</guid><description>&lt;p>IUGS President Qiuming Cheng announcing the DDE program at the opening of the DDE Forum.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CGI is a founding partner in the new IUGS big science program, the
&lt;a href="https://iugs.org/uploads/Reports/IUGS_Deep_Time_Digital_Earth_Launched.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Deep-time Digital Earth&lt;/a> (DDE). DDE was kicked off at the recent IUGS Executive Council meeting in Beijing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Recent CGI Meetings</title><link>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/recent-meetings/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2018 23:02:31 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://cgi-iugs.github.io/post/recent-meetings/</guid><description>&lt;p>Members of the EarthResourceML Working group met at IGME (the Spanish Geological Survey) in Madrid in May. L-R: Wang Yongzhi, Jouni Vuollo (chair), Mark Rattenbury, Ollie Raymond, Katarzyna Sadlowska, and Zhang Minghua.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The CGI Council and two of its standards working groups — Geoscience Terminology and EarthResourceML — convened in May in Madrid in conjunction with the
&lt;a href="http://www.geology.cz/gic" target="_blank" rel="noopener">34th Geoscience Information Consortium&lt;/a> (GIC) conference at the Spanish Geological Survey, IGME. Progress was made towards publishing several new geoscience vocabularies. Progress was also made towards publication of a new version of EarthResourceML (version 3.0), to address some issues identified by current users of the EarthResourceML v2.0 data transfer standard.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>